<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A description of the prosperitie, strength, and wise gouernment of the vnited Prouinces of the Netherlands Signified by the Batauian virgin, in her seat of vnitie. Wherein is related the whole state of those countries at this present time.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113182</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848421</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848421</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13514</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08071)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13514)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1321:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A description of the prosperitie, strength, and wise gouernment of the vnited Prouinces of the Netherlands Signified by the Batauian virgin, in her seat of vnitie. Wherein is related the whole state of those countries at this present time.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Edward Marchant,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A description of the prosperity of the vnited Prouinces.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Twelve Years' Truce, 1609-1621 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13514:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13514:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DESCRIPTION OF THE PROSPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RITIE, STRENGTH, AND WISE GOVERNMENT of the vnited Prouinces of <hi>the Netherlands.</hi> SIGNIFIED BY THE BATAVIAN VIRGIN, in her ſeat of vnitie. WHEREIN IS RELATED THE WHOLE ſtate of thoſe countries at this preſent time.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Felix Kingston, featuring two clasped hands emerging from clouds, holding a caduceus and two cornucopias (McKerrow 274)</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q> BY WISDOME PEACE BY PEACE PLENTY</q>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by FELIX KYNGSTON, for <hi>Edward Marchant.</hi> 1615.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:13514:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13514:2"/>
            <head>A DESCRIPTION OF THE PROSPERITY, STRENGTH, AND WISE GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the vnited Prouinces <hi>of the Netherlands.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <l>See how by wiſedome Hollands houſe doth flouriſh,</l>
               <l>And trust not Leopards craft that warre doth nouriſh.</l>
            </q>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A Friend to his natiue Countrey.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od ſaue you <hi>Batauian</hi> gentlewoman, I am very glad to ſee you thus triumphantly ſet in your throne of freedome, it ſeemes the world goes better with you now then it did in times paſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Batauian gentlewoman.</speaker>
               <p>In deede (my good friend) it is true that it is otherwiſe with me now then it was heretofore: for now (God bethanked) I am in my firſt and priſtinate ſtate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Is it better with you now (gentlewoman) then it was? and are you as you ſaid in your former ancient ſtate? and how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand you that? I pray you tell me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>My good friend, marke the particulars, as I ſhall ſet them downe plainely vnto you, and you ſhall eaſily vnderſtand it. I was long ſince, in former time a free State; but after that, I fell
<pb facs="tcp:13514:3"/>into great ſlauerie and bondage, and now at this preſent I am reſtored againe to my former liberty and free ſtate. For when my firſt founders came hither into this free countrey, which as that time belonged not vnto any man in perticular, but onely vnto thoſe that firſt tooke poſſeſſion thereof, and inhabited the ſame (according to the Law of nature,) in this free place they built me this houſe, which was called the <hi>Batauian</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and at this time the Holland Common-wealth, wherin I placed my ſeat or Throne, called freedome or liberty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Had you at the firſt no ſoueraigne Gouernour, that had the chiefe command ouer your houſe, and houſhold?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>The gouernment of my houſe was committed vnto two States, choſen and appointed out of mine owne people and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants; that is, the nobleſt and honourableſt men amongſt them, and the beſt and greateſt Citizens and inhabitants of the ſame. Theſe were the principall Commanders of my houſe and houſhold, who for the better gouernment thereof, made cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine cuſtomes and lawes for the ſtrengthening of peace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and had a great care ouer the ſame, for the preſeruation of the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>And in proceſſe of time, there was a principall perſon (as a King) choſen out of thoſe two States, who as the chiefeſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer or high Steward, had the principall command ouer it and the common-wealth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Then your forefathers in time paſt were gouerned after a princely manner by a chiefe Commander.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, Kings by name; as <hi>Veromerus,</hi> who was called the firſt <hi>Batauian</hi> King, who notwithſtanding was but the chiefe man, amongſt the principall perſons of the Land, and had the firſt command, and chiefe authoritie thereof.</p>
               <p>So were all the reſt that ſucceeded him, Kings ouer my <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauian</hi> Land, but had more authority to giue their counſell and aduice for the gouernment thereof, then power to command
<pb facs="tcp:13514:3"/>and rule ouer it. For the other Rulers and States that were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of the Nobilitie and Commons, had as much power or ſuperintendance ouer the King, as the King had ouer them, who with him together ruled the Land. But the King had an vpper command, or higheſt power permitted him, but not by authority or power, of, or in himſelfe: onely in regard and reſpect of his princely name he was obeyed, and his authority allowed with great reuerence and reſpect, and yet he himſelfe neuertheleſſe ſubiect to the Lawes of the Land, as is ordinary in electiue, not hereditarie Kings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Hereby I perceiue, that your houſe (called the <hi>Batauian</hi> Gouernment) from the very firſt originall thereof was a free Common-wealth, and your commonaltie, free people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>We were neuer ſubiect vnto any forraine Nations, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to our elected Gouernour and States, together with the lawfull and probable Lawes, made for the good gouernment thereof, whereunto euery man willingly ſubmitted himſelfe. In this ſtate we continued long time before the Romane Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, and were vnited vnto the ſame, and by her liued in peace, although the Romans had the ſole command and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the greateſt part of the world, and yet they were content to account of my forefathers, as their vnited friends; acknowledging my houſe to be a free State, and calling my houſhold ſeruants the <hi>Batauian</hi> commonaltie; and when they had any warres, and were aided by vs therein, they called vs their fellowes, and companions, (as <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> did,) and which is more, eſteemed vs as their brethren, friends, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted neighbours, in regard of the great aide and ſtrength they found at our hands, to helpe them in their need againſt their enemies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Then the Romans had no imperiall command ouer the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauian</hi> Countrey, when they were Monarches of the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>No. For my forefathers of <hi>Baetauia</hi> (according to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb facs="tcp:13514:4"/>Lawes) were ſtill gouerned by their owne people, which continued aboue an hundred yeeres, during the Romane Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, vntill ſuch time as their friendſhip turned into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and extreame oppreſſion, ſeeking to rob and ſpoyle mee and my Land, with pretence to turne my freedome into ſlauery and bondage, contemning our vnity, and wholly forgetting the forepaſſed friendſhip and aide by vs formerly ſhewed, and done vnto them. For which cauſe my forefathers tooke armes in hand, and began a lawfull warre, for the defence and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of mine honour and freedome, whereby the name of the Romans, in ſhort time, was wholy driuen away, &amp; cleane roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out, wherein perſonally they neuer had any abſolute au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority nor gouernment. For the which my <hi>Batauian</hi> people were ſo much honoured and eſteemed of, that as then they were called and held to be the authors of the freedome and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of our neighbours, and other Princes, who likewiſe were vnder the ſubiection of the Romans: but I obtained my free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome againe, and after that continued long in my free ſtate, and was gouerned by my two ſtates of the Land, vntill the ſauage Normans came and inuaded vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Was it then at that time that you began to be gouerned by Earles?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>I, but not as Soueraigne Gouernours, but onely choſen as chiefe Commanders, to ſerue in ſtead of Iudges, wee ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting our ſelues willingly vnder their command, eſteeming and holding them worthie to be our Protectors, and to haue the ſuperintendance ouer our <hi>Batauian</hi> gouernment, but had no power (by authority) to alter the Lawes and cuſtomes, nor to raiſe tolles, nor impoſitions, without the conſent and good will of the two States, but were bound by oath to defend and maintaine the Lawes and priuiledges of the Land, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect themſelues thereunto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Whereby it appeareth that neuer any Prince nor Earle had Soueraignty, or chiefe power alone, ouer you and your houſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:13514:4"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>No: for in the time of the Earles, there haue been ſome of them that by their bad gouernment and life, became oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Lawes and cuſtomes of the Land, and for that cauſe their authority was miſliked, and they put out of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. As it happened to the Ladie <hi>Iacobe,</hi> Counteſſe of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, from whom becauſe of her diſorders, and wilfulneſſe in her gouernment, againſt the priuiledges of the Land. The command ouer my houſe was taken away, and tranſported vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Philip</hi> Duke of Burgundie, which <hi>Batauian</hi> gouernment in proceſſe of time, and by marriages, was changed and fell into the houſe of Auſtria, and after that to <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Rome, (who with the good will and voices of all the States of my houſe) made ouer the <hi>Batauian</hi> Principality vnto his ſonne <hi>Philip,</hi> certifying him of my priuiledges, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of my ſubiects addicted vnto reſt and freedome, with an earneſt charge and warning giuen him, to haue a great regard and reſpect of the <hi>Batauian</hi> Common-wealth, and to gouerne them with a mild and fatherly affection: for that he eſteemed the ſame to be the beſt branch of his Crowne, which hee with Princely words and oathes promiſed to performe; but the contract being made, and he hauing the authority in his hands, wee ſtraight found a great alteration in our <hi>Batauian</hi> houſe; for that he being a Spaniard, both by birth and conditions, a great Prince, and very powerfull, and had the Soueraigne command ouer many Kingdomes, and Principalities, did not reſpect our <hi>Batauian</hi> liberty, nor once eſteemed our priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, but contrary to his promiſe, brake his Princely oath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>By this meanes your free State was turned into a bondage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>That is true, by this meanes my troubles began. For in ſtead of naturall borne Princes to protect my houſe, I got ſtrange outlandiſh waſters and deſtroyers thereof, who therein made a fearfull ſtur, with moſt ſtrange and great exactions, cruelties, and tyrannies ouer our liues and goods; to the end he might procure the breaking of the ancient authority of my priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
<pb facs="tcp:13514:5"/>the weakening of my lawes, and the aboliſhing of my liberty: But I ſeeing the beginning of my ouerthrow, the weake condition of my houſe, and the ſubuerſion of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, was compelled to ſeeke meanes for the preſeruation of my maidenly liberty, againſt thoſe that ſought to ſpoyle and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue me thereof; but finding my ſelfe in a manner very weak, by reaſon that diuers of my principall houſhold ſeruants fled from me, and that I was almoſt cleane ſpoyled of my houſhold ſtuffe, yea and my ſeat very neere taken from vnder me, which I had ſo long held and enioyed from my anceſtors, for that the feet thereof were almoſt drawne and broken each from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; whereby in a manner I ſat ſo wagling, that I could not deuiſe how I ſhould ſit faſter, by reaſon of my weake eſtate. But taking courage, I made meanes vnto my neighbours for aide; but where I expected ſecurity and ſupport, (ere I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware) I had like to haue been cleane ſpoyled: for by the aide that was ſent me, my houſe, Court, and Throne, was rather in worſe caſe then it was before.</p>
               <p>Whereupon my principall officers were by neceſſity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to ſeeke to marrie mee vnto ſome one, that by his aide they might haue meanes to helpe me and themſelues. But not long before I had had a good example ſet before mine eyes, of another maide, one of my neighbours, who by her welwillers was perſwaded to <hi>Handt-werpe,</hi> that is, to betroth her ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that ſought to bring her to <hi>Val-loos,</hi> that is, to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of her and all her people.</p>
               <p>This made me (I ſay) to goe to my croſſe neighbour, (who alſo was eſteemed a maide) to get ſome aide of her, to helpe to faſten my Seate, and thereby to hold a fit place to ſit in; for without that, they pretended to haue broken downe my <hi>Bata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uian</hi> houſe, and to haue made a bridge therof at their pleaſure, to haue gone ouer to my neighbours, thereby to obtaine the like dominion and power ouer them; and their meaning alſo was, vpon the old foundations and ruines of my <hi>Batauian</hi> houſe, to erect and build vp a new Spaniſh regiment, and to take my ſeate from me, and to turne it cleane ouer, as if I had had no voyce nor command therein: which made ſome of my
<pb facs="tcp:13514:5"/>fugitiue friends and welwillers to looke backe, and to ſtirre vp my neighbours, who as then vpheld and maintained me in my right, againſt thoſe that thought to haue thruſt mee cleane out of it, and by my ouerthrow to haue ouer-runne my neighbors, which was done by the commandement of that Spaniſh Earle, who as a fatherly protector was placed ouer me, according to his oath and promiſe to defend my maidenlike honour: but he ſought by ſtrange ruffians to violate mine honour, to ruinate my houſe and Court, (which notwithſtanding was one of his faireſt palaces) and alſo my houſhold ſeruants, eſteeming all as nothing; and which is more, ſought to make my people ſlaues, without once reſpecting my <hi>Batauian</hi> ſtate, which is a Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craticke gouernment. By this meanes (I ſay) hath hee by his vnſpeakeable tyrannicall gouernment, and vnlawfull vſurpari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, loſt the rule and pretended right (by my old cuſtomes and ancient priuiledges) that he had, by the aide and helpe of my neighbours and friends that ſtood in doubt of further miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe to come, aided by the power of the principall and chiefe Iudge of Iudges, who after 40. yeeres troubles, hath redcuced and placed me in my former ſeate of ancient freedome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlewoman, you haue now ſhewed me the ſtate of your old freedome, and withal of your troubles forepaſſed, whereof you ſay you are now freed. From hence forth therefore ſhew your maidenlike wiſedome, by calling to remembrance things paſt, wiſely to conſider of things preſent, &amp; well to foreſee that which is to come, and which concerneth you neere. Therefore let not your forepaſſed blowes (by a deceitfull bright ſunne-ſhining time) ſo ſoone be forgotten. For that many times after faire weather commeth a ſtorme, you doe well to ſit at your doore, to ſee whether it be cleere weather abroad; for in truth for theſe 40. yeeres together you haue endured many, and too many ſtormie winds, mightie raines, hailes, thunders, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and fierie flames.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaith very well and truly, that induſtrious labour makes a man rich. So haue I (by Gods helpe) and induſtrious
<pb facs="tcp:13514:6"/>labour, with defenſiue warre ouercome and withſtood the great force and power of my tyrannous enemie, and ſuch as haue by him been ouercome, and forced to flee their countrey, and to liue like ſtrangers in other countreyes; I haue with their wiues, children, and goods receiued into my houſe, and giuen them lodging therein. Whereby I got both thankes and furtherance, which to him was a weakening and enfeebling, and to me a ſtrengthening and fortification, which happened moſt hereabouts. But he fearing further miſchiefe, (perceiuing my fortunate proceedings,) was forced to ſeeke to me, (who at the firſt he contemned and eſteemed of no account; yea in a manner thought verily to bee his owne) to make peace with him, and to acknowledge me to be a free State, without once pretending to haue any right of gouernment ouer mee, and ſo I once againe got my long contentions (and almoſt cleane loſt) freedome into my hands. By the acknowledging and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of my enemies themſelues, who iudged it to bee my lawfull right, which in truth happened and came to paſſe by an accuſation of his owne conſcience, and a compulſiue neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, poſſeſſed with a deſperate hope of neuer to ouercome me. Theſe were the ſpeciall things that moued him thereunto, and not becauſe hee deſired peace, nor for any good will that hee bare vnto the welfare of my houſe, and houſhold ſeruants. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, I haue recouered mine ancient freedome, and hope to continue in this my maidenlike ſtate, by his aide and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull helpe that hath ſeene my miſery, and hath euidently in the ſight of all the world holpen and freed mee from the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh yoake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>God be praiſed, thanked, and glorified therefore, and to him muſt you pray, and in him firmely truſt. But it is commonly ſaid, that where there is no care, there is no feare: for while that you are now free and in good eſtate, you muſt bee carefull for your ſelfe and your houſhold, and that in twofold manner:</p>
               <p>Firſt, to looke well about you, that you be not deceiued nor ouer-runne by thoſe from whom you haue been deliuered, and haue freed your ſelfe from their bondage, becauſe they haue
<pb facs="tcp:13514:6"/>done that they did vpon meere neceſſity, and not for any loue they bare to you.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that you muſt bee prouident to prouide for that which is needfull and neceſſarie for you in time of need, that in time of want you run not to borrow corne of your neighbours to feed your geeſe withall: for a learned man wrote not in vaine, when he ſaid, Happie is that Land, which in time of peace thinketh vpon warre. And another learned Philoſopher teacheth vs, that a man muſt not truſt his recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled enemy too much: therefore now you ſit quietly and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in your houſe and poſſeſſions, it ſtandeth you vpon to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh your houſe well with 4. moſt neceſſarie things, wherein the whole, and all the ſtate thereof conſiſteth.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you muſt haue true, truſtie, and prouident houſhold ſeruants, ſuch as ſeeke not their owne good, but the profit of the common State, and thoſe that will not lightly by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues take any thing in hand, that may bee burthenſome and hurtfull to the Common-wealth, and the ſubiects thereof.</p>
               <p>Secondly, fit houſhold ſtuffe, ſuch as is honeſt, neceſſarie, ſeruiceable and furtherly in a houſe, to bee vſed for the ſeruice of the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, good prouiſion of ſuch things, as in ſuch a houſe (as yours is) are moſt neceſſarie and conuenient, as Cheſts, Ware-houſes, and ſellers, well furniſhed.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, you muſt ſpecially bee prouided of that wherewith you may doe moſt, and which by men is moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for that thereby you may get whatſoeuer you will, yea and almoſt as much as you will.</p>
               <p>All this is needfull for you to doe, whereof you are to haue a great care to bee prouided, that againſt an aſſault, or a hard and bad time, you may helpe your ſelfe, by your ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Alſo it is conuenient for the female kind (ſpecially a free maide as you are,) not to haue too much conuerſation with ſtrange men, ſpecially with ſuch as in times paſt ſought to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late your chaſtitie; yet I doubt not of your good behauiour in any wiſe, becauſe you haue already withſtood many aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, and by meanes of your honeſt minde and courage,
<pb facs="tcp:13514:7"/>haue hitherto ouercome all ſtormes whatſoeuer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>My good friend, I am warned to bee watchfull, but I hope God will preſerue and defend both me and my houſhold.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, I haue true and prouident houſhold ſeruants, in my <hi>Batauian</hi> dominion, (according to the ancient manner) firſt, an ouerſeer of the houſe, (called father of the Countrey,) then my two States, the nobleſt perſons of the Land, and the men of greateſt account among the Commons, who haue all the care, and ſpeciall charge of the ſtate of my houſe, both in peace and warre. Secondly, I haue conuenient and profitable houſhold ſtuffe, as good counſell, and vpright dealing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with my <hi>Batauian</hi> houſe is furniſhed, as with a heauenly and bright ſhining light, thereby to behold things paſt, to marke things preſent, and to foreſee things to come. The other are as inſtruments in needfull and profitable things, to ſerue the ſtate of the Land, (each one according to his qualitie and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) when time ſhall require. Thirdly, (God bee praiſed) my houſe is well prouided, (and daily more and more ſhall be) of that which ſhall ſerue for the Common-wealth, and ſuch as my houſholding requireth. Firſt, my Cheſts and Wardrops are well furniſhed with apparell of all ſorts; that is, of good iron dublets, ſteele gloues, ſtiffe ſhining collars, with the appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, all faire and well kept, that when I haue need of them they are readie at hand; my warehouſes are well prouided of fireage, which is made of black wood coales, brimſtone, &amp; falt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter, therewith eaſily to ſet fire on my turfe, which are round, and as hard as iron, and great heauie fiery arrowes, wherewith to make a good fire againſt winter and hard froſts. And for my ſellars, I haue yet a great many braſſe veſſels therein, to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch as come to viſit me, honourably; and in diuers ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges I haue many old geeſe, that when there is a faire, I may ſet ſome of them before my friends to welcome them withall. Now for that wherewith I can doe moſt, (which is money) I haue my vnited Commons, which are foure faithfull and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie labourers; that is, Husbandmen, Burgers of townes, Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, and Souldiers, (who at this time for a while are at their
<pb facs="tcp:13514:7"/>reſt, and liue quietly.) Theſe are all faſt bound together with the band of vnitie, and are they that at all times wil make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for my <hi>Batauian</hi> houſe, and Hollands garden, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I ſhall want. For my Husbandmen at this preſent are well prouided of corne, and other neceſſaries, and ſell it as deare, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, as they will or can, which alſo is apparant by the deck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his wiſe and children with gold and ſiluer which they daily weare. The towneſmen alſo build great and high houſes, which within are richly furniſhed with excellent faire houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſtuffe and moueables; as Tapiſtrie, ſiluer, and guilt plate, and hee himſelfe, and his wife and children, richly apparelled and ſmugd vp in ſilke and veluet, laid on with gold and ſiluer lace, making great bankets; all which are ſignes of proſperity, and are euery one induſtrious to maintaine themſelues in good eſtate; ſome by vſurie, others by trade at home, and ſome by merchandiſing, euery man ſtriuing not to bee the leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt. The Sailor ſaileth farre and wide for ſtrange merchandize; and if a rouer ſets vpon him at ſea, hee can play his part ſo well, that he ſhall get nothing at his hands; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times lookes himſelfe for ſuch a prize, ſo that it oft falleth out that he can ſaile with a by-legger, better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth when he ſaileth before the winde. But the Souldier likes not of this ſleepie calme weather, hee rather deſires to bee ruſtling in the field, to ſhew himſelfe a gallant. But the other three are very rich, and haue great meanes to helpe me, (I could not know it ſo well, but that they by their ſuperfluitie makes it manifeſt to all men) for which cauſe I and my houſhold are bound to haue a great care for them, and the Common wealth, for that they without me, and I without them, would bee a meanes to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw both me and my houſe, and alſo the commonaltie, and euery one of them in their perticular ſtates would come to nothing. For if the band of vnitie ſhould breake, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention become looſe, it would bee their deſtruction, and my ouerthrow out of my Throne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>I would faine ſee the pales of your gardens, and the manner of building about your houſe, or elſe of you heare the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb facs="tcp:13514:8"/>of the whole ſituation thereof, while you are now in a free ſtate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>My Holland garden is bordered about with a willow hedge or hurdle, called <hi>Fidelity;</hi> at the entry whereof there is a ſtile, ouer the which my watchfull (many eyed Lion) with his two forefeet ſtands looking, there to hold ſharpe watch. Then within, before the ſtile, and beninde the Lion, ſtandeth a high <hi>Orange</hi> tree, with a young ſprig or branch at the foot thereof, both comming out of an old root of a tree that hath been cut downe: round about this tree there is a root planted, called <hi>Gods bleſſing.</hi> In the middle of the garden there ſtandeth an old high ſtrong <hi>Piramides,</hi> called <hi>Priuiledge,</hi> cloſed about with a medicinable graft, called <hi>Gods grace.</hi> This garden is made of, and filled vp with good Holland earth, out of the which the Spaniſh vnfruitfull power is wholly rooted vp; and therefore in, and round about it there groweth <hi>Good will, Good courage; Heart hearbe; Care ſeede:</hi> (Ladie marke) alſo, <hi>Golden flowers, Siluer hearbes, Lance hearbes, Knights ſpurres, Horſe-mens herbe, Gun hearbe,</hi> and much <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Commendation.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Is not your garden ſomtimes weeded and cleanſed of weeds and hurtfull plants?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>Yea: ſor we were wont in times paſt to bee much troubled with great quantities of weedes; as with <hi>Force hearbe, Death hearbe, Catching roote, Feare hearbe, Pine apples, Blood herbe, Fier hearbe, Blacke hearbe,</hi> and <hi>Bitter gall nuts.</hi> But neceſſitie, and my houſhold ſeruants, appointed two officers to looke vnto it, (which were <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Power</hi>) each of them, as their turnes came, to weede it; for if it were not for theſe weeders, ſometimes there would ſome weeds grow vp in a nights ſpace before the Sun riſeth; as <hi>Romiſh thistle, Falſe lilies Fox hearbe, Strife flowers,</hi> and <hi>After-hurt.</hi> For not many yeers ſince, there grew a filthie hearb in my garden, called the <hi>Diuels Nay-thrid,</hi> and a hearbe called <hi>Diuels-beet,</hi> which ſtanke all ouer the garden, being of ſuch a nature, that whoſoeuer eate it, it made him enuious, and contentious; for it is of the kind of the ſeed
<pb facs="tcp:13514:8"/>of the apple whereof <hi>Eua</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> ate in Paradiſe, which then preſently cauſed great contention betweene God and them, and ſo it did now alſo; for whoſoeuer did eate thereof, thought that they were as wiſe as God, and knew all things, and for that cauſe thinking themſelues to be wiſe in their own conceits, they fell at ſtrife with their neighbours; but reaſon weeded out as much thereof as hee could, and in ſtead thereof planted a root called <hi>Part ſtrife,</hi> which in time will grow to be a great hearbe, but the diuels <hi>Nay-thrid,</hi> ran almoſt cleane through the whole garden, and hath made the <hi>Orange tree</hi> for certaine yeers to ſtand ſtil at a bay, and not to bloſſome, which maketh many heere amongſt vs to long for ſome of his fruit, if it were to be had; but the earth of my garden is ſo rich and fruitful, that if once a hot Spaniſh ſun-ſhine ſhould fall theron, (after the which a <hi>Batauian</hi> ſtroke-raine vſeth to follow) we ſhould preſently ſee the bloſſomes and fruit of the <hi>Orange tree</hi> ſhew forth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. Neuertheles we haue <hi>Oranges</hi> for a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſawce, and a good ſauour daily in my kitchin, and alſo for a refreſhing we haue the faire <hi>Orange lilie,</hi> and the <hi>Roſelike thiſtle flower,</hi> which is placed properly in ſeuerall beds in my garden.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Now I haue heard the manner of the ſituation of your gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: let me I pray you heare from you, what kind of building you haue in your houſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>The foundation of my houſe is named <hi>Vnity:</hi> the principals thereof are made of great ſtraight timber, lined and daubed with good vnited Netherlandiſh ſtones, the Hall thereof cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Batauian</hi> gouernment, is beautified with eight faire cleere windowes, and in the middle of them all ſtandeth one ſpecially, as a principall ſhield beautifying the ſame. The roofe of the houſe is couered ouer with faire ſhining ſhels, which couer is called <hi>Hardineſſe.</hi> The entrie or gate thereof is named <hi>Victory:</hi> the poſts and top of it are couered ouer with greene hearbes, in the middle whereof my ſeate ſtandeth, called <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi> made of firme ground wood: and aboue all the reſt the ſigne of my houſe is <hi>Emanuel.</hi> Now my friend, you haue heard
<pb facs="tcp:13514:9"/>and vnderſtood the manner and forme of my houſe and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, wherein at this preſent I haue and hold my free habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which, of almoſt a deſperate loſt inheritance, I haue made free againe, more by honeſt meanes, and true and lawfull right, then by forcible craftineſſe, although my ill willers behind my backe report and ſay, that I decke my ſelfe with ſtrange fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when as they notwithſtanding lurke and hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnder my wings; neuertheleſſe I haue ſtriuen as much for their freedomes, as I haue done for mine owne naturall and good peoples liberty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Gentletwoman, Doe you perceiue that which I ſee there, which is a ſtrange ſhow, it ſeemeth to bee a twin, or a body of two kindes, whereof the one halfe before ſeemeth to laugh friendly vpon you, with a ſweet womanlike face; and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther halfe behinde, is armed with a cruell ſouldiers looke, and hath a monſtrous great beaſt by him, wherein I take no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>This partie hath been heere ſome few yeeres ſince, and brought that beaſt with him into our <hi>Batauian</hi> houſe; but what ſhall I doe, ſeeing he lookes ſo ſmilingly vpon me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in outward ſhew, or in action, I will not as yet quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with him and miſtruſt him, before he leaues laughing, and then I will ſee, (and alſo aske him) what hee meaneth to doe, that he commeth here into my garden with ſuch a hinder part, and ſo faire and pleaſant a forepart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you not thinke that he can ſoone turne that laughing countenance behind him from you, and place the bitter looke before: It was wont to be the Italian manner, and the Spaniſh cuſtome: ſee you not that hee hath turned the hinder part of his face towards a troupe of ſouldiers, and the forepart towards you; the while that he with outward flearing face lookes on you: with the hinder part hee doth expect your ouerthrow; therefore it is fit that the Lion ſhould take good heed vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>But (my friend) doe you know what manner of man this is,
<pb facs="tcp:13514:9"/>and doe you know the beaſt well? I haue long time caſt mine eyes thereon: let me heare what your iudgement is of him, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you ſhew your ſelfe to bee ſo carefull for me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>The happineſſe of your ſtate makes mee ſo carefull for you, but in my iudgment this man is one of the foure ſorts or kinds of <hi>Hermaphrodites,</hi> (which are both men and women,) which is one of the worſt kind of creatures that are liuing vpon the earth, if they may (without reſtraint) vſe and ſhew forth their nature. For they can ſuffer themſelues to be dealt withall in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of weake and effeminate women, with faire ſhewes, and ſweet words to deceiue withall; and as a woman by nature is milde, they can bring their ſubtill practiſes, and deceitfull charmes to paſſe, which if they effect not in two or three yeeres, they doe it in 6. or 8. and ſomtimes in 10. or twelue.</p>
               <p>Againe, theſe <hi>Hermophrodites</hi> (when they liſt) can bee like cruell and ſturdie men, and can as well by force as by craft bring many things to paſſe, for they are without all meaſure wicked and hollow hearted.</p>
               <p>Which for you (being a maide) is very dangerous, for thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to ſee a womanlike face, and to heare an effeminate voyce, you ſhould with the turning of an hand fall into a ſnare, and be deflowred, whereby your moſt noble and great fame ſhould be ouerthrowne, and your praiſe-worthie name cleane defaced.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Batauia,</hi> this is my iudgement, and a forewarning for you concerning this perſon, and where you thinke this great ſweet ſhining noſegay to be a Palme branch, it is not ſo; for it is a branch of a hearbe called <hi>Munkes hood,</hi> a venomous hearbe, which heretofore was rooted out of your garden, which hee hath taken vp again, therewith to bring you at length into a ſound ſleepe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>What thinke you of that monſtrous beaſt, what beaſt, and of what kinde and nature is it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>That may well and eaſily be ſeene and iudged by the ſpeck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:13514:10"/>skin that it hath, which is like a <hi>Nay-ed</hi> or patcht Monkes gowne; and therefore I thinke that it is naturally a <hi>Leopard,</hi> which is a greedie blood ſucking beaſt, begotten of a <hi>Lioneſſe,</hi> by a <hi>Panther;</hi> and therefore it is called by a double ſignifying name, a <hi>Leopard.</hi> This beaſt although it is brought forth by a ſhee <hi>Lion,</hi> yet it is moſt greedie and eruelly bent to ſeeke the deſtruction of the male <hi>Lion:</hi> but as it is bloodily minded, ſo it is ſubtill and craftie, ſpecially to intrap his greateſt enemy the <hi>Lion,</hi> therby to fall vpon him and to deſtroy him: to the which end he is skilfull how to make double holes, one aboue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which run both into one, being wide aboue, and narrow or ſtraite in the middle, whereinto he runneth, to get the <hi>Lion</hi> (following him) betweene them both, and ſo to entangle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe therein; in the meane time the <hi>Leopard</hi> leapes out at the other hole, and falleth vpon the backe of the <hi>Lion,</hi> for by that meanes the <hi>Lion</hi> cannot vſe his ſtrength againſt him; and ſo he ſheweth his deceitfull nature and condition, which by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie he practiſeth and bringeth to paſſe.</p>
               <p>And yet at other times he hath ſhewed other <hi>Leopards</hi> tricks vpon the African <hi>Apes,</hi> and Weſt-Indian <hi>Monkeyes:</hi> for vpon a time when hee ſpied many of them together, hee made as though he had been dead, or aſleepe; in the meane time the <hi>Apes</hi> and <hi>Monkeyes</hi> came without feare out of their holes, (thinking to be free &amp; out of doubt) and were very ioyful, and played many apiſh toyes one with the other, not doubting any thing, nor once ſo much as dreaming of the riſing vp againe of their ſlumbring enemie, who like a <hi>Leopard</hi> lay lurking, and ſeeing time fit and conuenient, when thoſe beaſts were vnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and without feare, he roſe vp out of his counterfeit ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and falling vpon them, deuoured and tare in ſunder the moſt part of them. This (Gentlewoman) ſerueth alſo for a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to you: for not long ſince, I heard you ſay, that you yet haue many old geeſe for prouiſion for your kitchin, whoſe cages you are to looke well to, leſt this <hi>Leopard</hi> with craftie baytes and force comes not ſuddenly and deuoureth them, as he hath already deuoured many <hi>Lions</hi> and <hi>Monkeys,</hi> and the ſame would hee doe vnto your owne perſon alſo, if hee
<pb facs="tcp:13514:10"/>had the meanes according to his will.</p>
               <p>I meane this leering ſuiter, who with a craftie diſſembling manner of ſuite, though not openly, ſeeking to get as neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you as he can, as you may perceiue by his entry into <hi>Gulicke,</hi> and <hi>Cleaueland,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Marke,</hi> and meaneth not to leaue ſo, vntill he hath gotten ſomething that may further his pretence for the warre, not by skirmiſhes, thereby to ſet forth your honour the more (which hee thinketh before this time to haue ſufficiently tried) but by long and continuall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie in the end to lay hold vpon you by force.</p>
               <p>For he accounts you already to bee his owne, although ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe (of meere neceſſity) hee did acknowledge you to be a free State.</p>
               <p>But as he knoweth the nature of diuers ſlaues whom he hath vnder his ſubiection, and perceiues well that hee muſt not vſe them one like another, to keepe them in bondage, and to get more, he hath therein a ſpeciall watch vpon you, for the <hi>Ango<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Sentomiſh,</hi> and <hi>Guineian</hi> Moores, were with great cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty made his ſlaues, and with ſeueritie held in bondage. Whereas the <hi>Braſilian</hi> Nation were by deceit and policy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued of their freedome, and made his, and by compulſion holden ſlaues.</p>
               <p>Now marke well Gentlewoman; at the firſt hee ſought to you, now he begins to worke otherwiſe: in time paſt he began it by cruel <hi>Alua,</hi> whereby he put you into ſo great a feare, that hee was forced to call backe his executioner for your people were ſo wilde, that they from himſelfe (as the author of the execution) got a diſcharge of him, ſo that thereupon came a great <hi>Commander,</hi> with a pardon for your obſtinacie towards him, who miniſtred ſuch Spaniſh figs (called pardons) that thereby you were almoſt choaked in the mier, and many of you died. After him came <hi>Don Iohn de Auſtria,</hi> to pacifie you, who at firſt ſeemed ſomewhat to encline to a peace, but in ſhort time after he made an vproare amongſt you againe. For that cauſe there was a ſtrange preſent ſent (but yet for more furtherance to his intent.) which was an Italian <hi>Parmaſan:</hi> but perceiuing that it was too ſweet for your taſte, and not liked
<pb facs="tcp:13514:11"/>of, he let the <hi>Parmaſan</hi> rot, and began to come vpon you with a haſtie <hi>Duch-Earuſt:</hi> but becauſe your <hi>Batauians</hi> are milde of nature, and can ſee farre, hee tooke no pleaſure in ſuch <hi>Erust</hi> proceeding: then hee ſent a red ſhining Spirituall man, that ſhould make <hi>Albright,</hi> and cleare, thinking to ouercome your perſon, and the <hi>Batanian</hi> gouernment with his <hi>Claer Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious</hi> wit and behauiour, which he put in practiſe; but all in vaine: after that he came with craftie <hi>Spinners,</hi> (and now with leering <hi>Leopards</hi>) but the <hi>Spinners</hi> webbe was too weake to catch you in: for that cauſe he ſpread another <hi>Nay-d,</hi> or broad net, which hee caſt ouer your head; but it is ſo looſe and ſo wide, that you can ſee cleerely through it, vnleſſe that the ſhew of the noſe gay ſhould make your head ſo diſſie, that by means of the venomous ſmel thereof, you ſhould fall aſleepe, and that is it which this leering <hi>Leopard</hi> lookes for: to bring you firſt to the <hi>Braſilian</hi> ſlauerie, then to deale with you as with the <hi>Guineans;</hi> and laſtly, with the <hi>Weſt-indians.</hi> Therefore preſerue your freedome, and alſo ſhew that you are free; let not others appoint your lawes concerning that which toucheth you, for the preſeruation of your houſe, and the defending of your next neighbours, which concerneth your ſelfe much, for which this <hi>Leopard</hi> hath long leered (Shipper looke out.)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>My good friend, wee are well acquainted in my houſe with the nature and conditions of this <hi>Leopard,</hi> we haue often heard his howling in our garden, but yet we beleeue him not. To that end my many waking eied <hi>Lion</hi> ſtands before the ſtile and looks out; and this <hi>Leopard</hi> muſt not thinke that he is in Weſt-India; for in ſtead of <hi>Monkeys,</hi> I would ſend great ſtore of <hi>Graſhoppers</hi> after him, which are eaſily to bee ſound in my gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and I haue neſts, yea whole regiments of <hi>ſwift</hi> flies, (<hi>a fig for</hi> the Spaniſh flies) which neſtle vnder my <hi>Orange tree,</hi> which with their ſharpe pricking <hi>Augls,</hi> will ſo pricke and ſting him through his ſpeckled skinne, that you ſhall heare him howle into Spaine, to call for helpe. But my water-fowles (that are very cunning in ſwimming) would ſo well watch the coaſts and hauens there, that not one <hi>Leopard</hi> (which are but <hi>Flutte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13514:11"/>in the water) ſhal not dare to thruſt their heads out of their holds, for my water-fowles are very ſharpely ſet againſt the <hi>Leopards,</hi> becauſe at other times he hath often taken their egs out of their neſts, and puld away many of their feathers, and hath cut many of them ſhort, ſomtimes when they were wont with great danger to ſwimme ouer the Spaniſh ſeas, into the Spaniſh hauens, which they yet remember well, and can better reuenge themſelues then the <hi>Monkeys.</hi> For firſt my <hi>Graſhoppers</hi> for the moſt part of them, are old <hi>Leapers,</hi> that haue good skill to leape vpon the water-ſides, and the hard land, as they in times paſt did vpon Turenholt <hi>Heath,</hi> and Newport ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrand: but ſince that time they haue brought forth many young ones, who are well learned and inſtructed by the old ones, and can match the flies well enough, who alſo are old and well experienced; for they were wont in times paſt, luſtily to flie vpon the Canary, and S. <hi>Thomas</hi> Suger; and alſo vpon the figs and reaſons of <hi>Calis malis,</hi> which was good meate for them; but my water-fowles are ſo ſwift in flying, that their nimbleneſſe is known in Eaſt-India, where they at other times haue luſtily flowne vpon their Nutmeg bloſſomes, and there left the ſmell and ſauour of the Netherlands <hi>Mateliue,</hi> whereat they did not greatly reioyce; yea they are ſo quicke and ſtrong in flight, that they flie vp through ſtrange water and waies to <hi>Heemſche-kercke,</hi> there to hold the <hi>Iubile,</hi> and they bite ſo ſore, that there is no Spaniſh <hi>Nut</hi> but they will bite it in peeces, how hard ſoeuer it be. In ſwimming alſo they are very craftie, and ſtout, ſpecially vpon a Spaniſh fleeet, to bee maſters of it with a ſmall power, whereby in Spaine they are called water-Diuels, (without once remembring that God is their Pilot) And though this <hi>Leopard</hi> is a great enemie to the <hi>Lions,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he hath deceiued and taken many, yet he hath not found the meanes to be guile them all, as it appeareth; for in my <hi>Batauian</hi> houſe, there ſtandeth or ſitteth yet ſeuen that lookes out at the window:</p>
               <p n="1">1 Firſt, my <hi>Hollands</hi> rampant <hi>Lion:</hi>
               </p>
               <l>Who although he doth neere leaue climing ſtill,</l>
               <l>he's not ſo high as he would by hit will.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13514:12"/>
               <p n="2">2 Next him the <hi>Zelands</hi> ſwimming <hi>Lion</hi> ſtands:</p>
               <l>Who alſo hath a head and liues thereby,</l>
               <l>And for the <hi>Libard</hi> careth not a flie.</l>
               <p>For although he hath ſwome long time, he is not yet drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if occaſion once ſerued he would make the <hi>Leopard</hi> dance vpon the water, but it ſhould be no apiſh dance.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In a higher window there ſtands a <hi>Gelders</hi> Lion.</p>
               <l>This holds a place iuſt in the <hi>Libards</hi> way,</l>
               <l>And when he thinkes to paſſe, will make him ſtay.</l>
               <p n="4">4 In the window beneath him there are two <hi>Freeſeland</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons readie to run;</p>
               <l>Not for to run away out of his ſight,</l>
               <l>But t'hinder his pretence to his deſpight.</l>
               <p n="5">5 Then there is two other <hi>Lions,</hi> each of them in a window apart, whereof the one,</p>
               <l>Stands not in <hi>Ouer Iſel</hi> t'haue a ſight</l>
               <l>Of leering <hi>Libard,</hi> but with him to fight.</l>
               <p n="6">6 In the other window is the <hi>Zutphen</hi> Lion:</p>
               <l>Which if the <hi>Libard</hi> ſhould begin to baul,</l>
               <l>Would luſtily with's clawes vpon him fall.</l>
               <p n="7">7 In a high window at the vpper part of my houſe:</p>
               <l>The luſtie, ſtrong, and valiant <hi>Vtrechts</hi> Knight,</l>
               <l>Doth watch, and hath the <hi>Libard</hi> ſtill in ſight.</l>
               <p>And in the vpper part of my houſe:</p>
               <l>Th'Eaſt <hi>Frieſland</hi> quicke ſight Eagle lookes about,</l>
               <l>With's wings abroad to ſee how things fall out.</l>
               <p>And how high ſoeuer hee ſeemes to ſit, yet if the <hi>Leopard</hi> begins once to play his part, he would ſoon fle vpon his back: for it is moſt certaine, that all of them together, and euery one of them particularly is well acquainted with the blood-thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtineſſe, cruelty, and craftineſſe of the <hi>Leopard;</hi> and haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to what end he comes thus leering hereabout, euery one of them thinking that he leereth vpon him; and therefore they all ſtand vpon their guard, and would rather willingly leape vpon him, then ſuffer him to lay hold on them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>I am of the ſame opinion alſo, Gentlewoman, and I thinke
<pb facs="tcp:13514:12"/>that all your foure men, whom you tearme your truſtie huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band men, before you ſhould bee throwne downe, would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a time leaue their tilling the land, ſeafaring and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſing, and ſet their wiues on worke for the vpholding of your perſon, and they themſelues with the Souldiers, (whom they would ſoone raiſe out of their ſleep) would march againſt the <hi>Leopard,</hi> for the defence of your <hi>Batauian</hi> gouernment, and the keeping of the Hollands garden: yea, &amp; before that you for want of meanes, or by reſtraint ſhould be forced to leaue your ſeat of freedome, your Commons would rather labor for you, till they ſweat blood, and yet too great toles and heauie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens are cumberſome to labouring men; but the loue they beare to you, and the hope they haue of their happineſſe by your freedome, would make them forget the paines they take, for the furtherance of the Common-wealth: but the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Sea-faring men, and Citizens, altogether with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, (to bring their purpoſe the better to effect,) wiſh that the Souldier alſo were awake with them. For a common but then ſeems a common eaſe, but an aſſured common reſt &amp; quietnes is better, although your men apply themſelues to the time. For which cauſe, willing labourers that are tied together in the bands of vnity, deſerue ſome furtherance, and for that you are all their naturall mother, it learnes euery one both great and ſmall, together and apart, to ſhew their good wils and duties vnto you in that reſpect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>That is true, for my State is coſtly to beare all the charges that are neceſſarily to be laid out, ſpecially now I am ſet againe in my free Seate; therefore I would, if I could, bring it ſo to paſſe, that no man ſhould haue any cauſe to finde fault, thereby to make all man free in our garden.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
               <p>Then it is requiſite and very needfull to haue a good regard that the <hi>Leopard</hi> makes no double holes for the <hi>Lion,</hi> that you need not ſtand in doubt at what hole to watch for him, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to looke well to that double face, and to haue an eye to the troupe of men that ſtands yonder, for it ſeemeth that they are
<pb facs="tcp:13514:13"/>at a ſtand, and would bee gone away: but me thinkes rather that they encreaſe and ſeeme to come neerer; and in the meane time this forepart giueth you a faire ſmiling countenance, and the hinder part is for their furtherance; and therefore a farre off they aſſemble ſpeedily and hold together.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Batauia.</speaker>
               <p>Therfore we will commend the watch to our chiefe watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Emanuel,</hi> and commit the charge of our houſe to him, and altogether from henceforth will be vigilant, and looke well to the craftie fetches of the <hi>Leopard;</hi> for if I were ſure that hee would leeringly come too neere mee, and that his face would turne about, I would preſently let my <hi>Lion</hi> looſe to flie vpon the <hi>Leopard,</hi> and wake my Souldier, to beard that marſhall face, who thinketh that he that ſlumbreth is faſt aſleepe, but the noiſe would ſoone awake him.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Distrust and watch th'enemie to withſtand,</l>
                  <l>Concord and faithfulneſſe in Towne and Land,</l>
                  <l>Are weapons ſure and ſtrong:</l>
                  <l>But before all theſe things, vpon him call,</l>
                  <l>And chiefly trust in him that can doe all</l>
                  <l>By's power, and right thy wrong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>BAtauian Virgin faire,</l>
                  <l>That ſits in freedomes chaire,</l>
                  <l>Victoriouſly and well:</l>
                  <l>Looke to thy enemy,</l>
                  <l>That on thee caſts his eye.</l>
                  <l>Beware of Libard fell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>Where falſe loue cannot win,</l>
                  <l>To hate thee they begin,</l>
                  <l>For when loue waxeth cold,</l>
                  <l>Then hatred for good will,</l>
                  <l>Makes them ſeeke thee to kill.</l>
                  <l>Truſt not the Libard bold.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13514:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>Sowre ſawce diſtaſts ſweet meate.</l>
                  <l>Craft th'upper hand doth get.</l>
                  <l>Reuonge breakes peaces lawes.</l>
                  <l>The thing that's not ſtraight wonne,</l>
                  <l>May chance in time be done.</l>
                  <l>Keepe out the Libards clawes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>He that firſt bragd of thee,</l>
                  <l>That thou his owne ſhould be,</l>
                  <l>But nothing thereby got.</l>
                  <l>After long warre ſeemes meeke,</l>
                  <l>And maketh ſhew to ſeeke</l>
                  <l>Thy loue. Beleeue him not.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>Though he ſaid thou ſhouldſt haue,</l>
                  <l>Thy liberty, and gaue</l>
                  <l>Conſent to't in his need.</l>
                  <l>He ſeekes to ſpoyle thee now,</l>
                  <l>If that he could tell how.</l>
                  <l>Of Libards wiles take heed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>Thy true loue holdes him backe,</l>
                  <l>Thy trustie friends doe make</l>
                  <l>Him feare, and therefore hee,</l>
                  <l>Tintrap thee if he may</l>
                  <l>Doth lurke. Wherefore I ſay,</l>
                  <l>Of him ſtill warie be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>Fight in thy friends defence,</l>
                  <l>If he will not goe thence</l>
                  <l>In time, ſith he doth ſo,</l>
                  <l>Torment them, for thy ſake,</l>
                  <l>Reuenge their wrong, and make</l>
                  <l>Him out the field to goe.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13514:14"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <l>Faire Hollands Princely Dame,</l>
                  <l>Maintaine thy ancient fame,</l>
                  <l>Be not at his command:</l>
                  <l>Although t'is his intent.</l>
                  <l>Doe nought thou maiſt repent.</l>
                  <l>Gainst Libard boldly ſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Printed ſomewhere in the</hi> Batauian <hi>Land,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My name if you deſire to vnderſtand:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It is, (as men me commonly doe call,)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Pleaſant, Rich, and Famous</hi> Hollands <hi>Hall.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13514:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
